- Hey folks, and welcome
to the Learn UI Design
lesson on Luminosity.
Now, luminosity is probably one
of the most important topics
in all of color and UI Design.
And yet, to be honest,
you basically hear no
one talking about it.
So in this lesson,
we're gonna take a look.
Now I'll say that luminosity
is kind of a fourth property
of color that is separate from hue,
separate from saturation,
separate from brightness and yet,
related to all three of those things.
I'll explain exactly what
it is and how it works
and I'll also of course, be
showing you a couple examples
on mobile and desktop of
how you can use luminosity
to fix very common problems
in user interface design.
Alright, you ready?
Let's get started.
So the example we're
gonna start with is kind
of this Fitness app
that I have right here.
And I've just thrown together
some stuff on the page,
don't look too much into the specifics.
The real point here is this is realistic,
and that a lot of times,
you'll start on a design
project for a new client,
and they might say, hey,
when we add the logo design,
we got these two colors,
these are our brand colors,
yellow, turquoise, I want you to use them.
And so you start designing
out stuff and you think, okay,
I'm gonna apply these brand colors,
but you quickly find out
that there's actually
some issues there and you
can't just kind of slap
them on wherever you want.
Well, I'm gonna talk about
some of those issues.
And I'm also gonna talk about how knowing
and understanding luminosity
can help you solve those issues.
So issue number one, you
can probably see this even
before I zoom in, but when I zoom in,
it's just especially obvious.
These colors are both just a lot.
They're very bright in your
face and they kinda clash
and it almost like hurts
my eyes a little bit
to stare at the screen.
I feel like for too long.
And yet these are the
colors we have, right?
So what are we gonna do about it?
How are we gonna help fix this?
Individually, they might be fine
but especially when taken together,
there's just a lot going on.
Now part of the issue here is both
of these colors are very bright.
So if I use my little color
picker, Control C, you can see
this is 97% brightness, and
this has 100% brightness.
And so maybe your first instinct
is to do something like take
the yellow and just move
the brightness down a little bit.
Here I moved it down 20.
But if I move it down 20, all of a sudden,
this does not look yellow anymore.
And actually turns out that yellow,
if you bring it under about
90% brightness in HSB,
it just kinda loses that yellow field.
So that solution is not gonna work.
Now maybe your next guest is to say, hey,
maybe I'd mess with the
brightness of this turquoise.
But what I wanna show you is something
that might actually be kind of surprising.
So yeah, this turquoise is bright,
it's 100% brightness but we're not looking
at solely a brightness problem.
If I take the hue slider
and just kinda move
it on over into this blue range to 48
is like basically focused on blue,
although this is coming
out a little more indigo,
almost purple.
But if I switch that theme color,
there's no problem anymore, right?
This yellow just does not
contrast in the same way.
Or Honestly, it contrasts
better and it doesn't clash
in the same way.
And yet, check this out, I
didn't change the brightness,
this has a brightness of 100%.
And all this raises an
interesting sort of contradiction.
This has a brightness
of 97 so basically 100,
this has a brightness of 100,
and this has a brightness of 100.
And yet, if you showed them
to someone on the street
and said which one of these is brighter,
they would undoubtedly pick the yellow.
And they would say that this
kind of Indigo ish color
is certainly the darkest of these three.
So there has to be more
to the brightness story
than just whatever the B value
is in the HSB color system.
And there is, that something
else is called luminosity.
And it's sort of refers
to the natural brightness
of a particular color.
The HSB brightness is
sort of as we described
in the last lesson,
it's kind of how on is
that light bulb, right?
It goes from black to some
very bright version of a color.
But there's kind of this
other brightness scale
that is independent of those.
And that's actually what we
wanna take a look at here.
So one way to tap into this
other brightness scale,
this natural brightness of luminosity
and this is the best way to
do it in Figma, honestly,
is to grab one of these
colors, and go to blend mode,
which in Figma is this
little like teardrop kind
of icon shape, and go all the way down
to luminosity blend mode.
And unfortunately, I'm gonna
have to do this three times.
But you can see what
it's done is changed each
of these colors to gray.
There's really no hue,
there's zero saturation,
and there's just a brightness of the gray.
And what's interesting is
when we change these colors
to luminosity blend mode, the
brightness of the gray sort
of corresponds to the natural
brightness of the color.
So these two colors, both very bright,
and we get as the luminosity output a gray
with a brightness of 82.
This purple ish color Indigo
adds a little bit darker
and sure enough,
when it gets put into
luminosity blend mode,
it only has a brightness of 52%.
Just to be totally clear technically,
designers kind of misuse the
words luminance and luminosity
and the definitions are a little bit messy
and kind of mangled together.
Scientists actually have
two different precise things
that they mean here.
And so this blend mode
brightness of the gray,
that is not like an official
measure of luminosity
that goes from some scale to zero to 100,
that other people outside of UI design
would actually know about
if you talked about it.
But it is useful as kind
of a relative measure
of relative to these other colors,
which one is sort of the naturally
that has the most brightness to it,
and which has the kind of
the is naturally the darkest.
So just bear that in mind,
we're not talking about
some official measure
of like photons hitting
your eye or whatever.
We're just sort of saying, okay,
this is we're gonna call
this a 52 luminosity,
and we're gonna call
this an 82 luminosity.
Now, you might be wondering,
if in going from this turquoise color,
which has a saturation of
53, and a brightness of 100,
to this purple color, which
is a very similar saturation
and an identical brightness,
if in doing that,
just shifting the hue I got
this drastic change in luminosity.
What exactly is the pattern there?
What's going on?
Well, here's the pattern,
I'll show you here,
this is also on the color cheat sheet,
which is linked below.
But the gist of it is,
is all colors have a natural
luminosity, and it changes
with hue, saturation, and
brightness but hue is perhaps
the most interesting pattern here.
You can see I've taken all the
hues of the rainbow laid out
from zero degrees to 360 degrees.
And I've taken the
swatches at 100% brightness
and 100% saturation for each of these
so you're just looking
at a change in hue here.
And then I tracked what
is the luminosity along
that entire color wheel.
And what you can see is that
there's certain high points
and low points.
And very interestingly, the
low points are this red,
because it certainly rises as you increase
the hue from here,
it also rises as you
decrease the hue from 360.
So the red is one low point,
the green is another low point
and the blue is a third low point.
Likewise, the high points
are yellow at 60 degrees,
the cyan color at 180 degrees,
and this kind of magenta at 300 degrees.
If you've done much design work,
you may recognize that RGB for red, green,
blue is the most popular color system used
and CMY or cyan, magenta, yellow,
and sometimes black is added as a K, CMYK.
That's another color system
used by print designers.
And you might be wondering,
is this a coincidence?
No, it turns out it's not.
Although the exact reason why red,
green and blue are the
low points and yellow,
cyan and magenta are the high points?
It's a little bit outside
the scope of this video,
so I have explained it below.
Nonetheless, the practical
part of what you need to know,
is whenever you have some
color, let's say it's an orange,
and you want to raise the
luminosity of that orange,
you want to make it
appear naturally brighter,
you can subtly shift
the hue towards yellow
which means increasing the hue.
As you do that the natural brightness
will increase until the
point where you hit a hue
of 60 degrees.
And if you keep increasing the
hue, that natural brightness
kind of just someone on
the street saying, hey,
this color looks brighter than that color,
that natural brightness is gonna start
to decrease again until
you hit 120 and so on
and it goes all the way
around the circle of hues.
Likewise, if you had that
orange and wanted to make
it naturally darker,
then you could slide it
down towards zero degrees.
And that's true for basically
any point on this chart,
except for the high point.
From a high point you can
only make the luminosity less,
you can move in either way,
and it's gonna make the luminosity lower.
But for every other point
besides a high point
or a low point, you have one
direction that's gonna make
it naturally a little bit
brighter, and the other direction,
that's gonna make it
naturally a little bit darker.
So what that tells me for this
app here is what I wanna do
is move away from 180 degrees, that cyan,
that's kind of that natural high point.
Now as I do that, if I just
start making jumps of 10,
pretty soon even going 20 degrees higher,
I kind of lose some of the
feel of that turquoise.
And so I know okay,
I don't actually wanna go quite that high.
But even so much is going
up to 192 from 185 is going
to do something to kind
of decrease the luminosity
of this blue and thereby make
it clash a little bit less
against this yellow.
Now just in the way that
luminosity depends on the hue,
and changing the hue will give
you a different luminosity,
the same thing is also true
of saturation and brightness.
So let's start with brightness
because that works exactly
how you would expect it.
What I have here is a
number of squares of red,
this is a hue of zero and the saturation
of all these reds is 100%, okay?
So the hue of this red and
the saturation stays constant
the entire line across.
The only thing that changes
is the brightness goes from 0% to 100%.
Now, if I take these 11 squares,
and I duplicate them,
and then I put them in
luminosity blend mode,
I can see that what happens
is the natural brightness,
the luminosity goes from zero.
Black is the least luminous color,
it has no luminosity whatsoever.
It goes from zero all the way up to here,
where I have this value of 30.
Okay, cool now, that's
not just true of this red
at 100% saturation,
it's true of literally every single color.
If you increase the brightness,
you also increase the luminosity,
the natural brightness,
that should make perfect sense.
The thing that's a little
bit tougher to remember
is that luminosity and
saturation go in opposite ways.
When I increase the saturation,
I'm actually decreasing the luminosity.
So here I have the same thing going on.
All of these swatches are
at hue zero for just kind
of a pure red, and they're
all at brightness 100.
The only thing that
changes is the saturation,
which I've taken from 0% to
10% to 20, all the way to 100%.
If I just check out what that looks like
in luminosity blend mode,
it's the same thing but
interestingly enough,
you'll notice I'm going
from a luminosity of 100,
that's white, down to a luminosity of 30.
And that luminosity moves down
while the saturation is moving up.
One just mental check you
can do if you feel like
this is getting confusing,
is just think about white,
white is the most luminous color.
Just as Black has a luminosity of zero,
White has a luminosity of 100%.
And yet white always has 0% saturation.
So you can always think
that if you're trying
to make something more luminous,
you're moving it towards white.
And that kind of ties it
in to practically speaking
what we've seen in over
the last couple of lessons,
where I move things up into the left
for them to be like
white or more luminous.
And I move these colors
down and to the right,
if I want them to be less luminous
or kind of naturally darker.
The big point of this lesson, though,
is that I have the option of moving hue,
saturation and brightness,
I just have to know which
direction to move each.
So going back to our Fitness app,
let's keep playing with this
little turquoise color here.
Now one thing I do with colors,
I kind of obey my own maxim
of fail left, fail right.
You might have noticed when I
was adjusting this turquoise,
I went a little bit too
high until I feel like,
you know what this is actually
more of like a blue just kind
of a soft blue color doesn't
have that turquoise field
doesn't quite feel as beachy as this.
And yet, at 192, this
feels a little bit better.
It's not exactly the same
as a hue of 185 here,
but honestly, if your client
tells you to use this color,
and you use this color,
they probably won't even notice
it's feels like a very natural variation.
And that largely is
what we're trying to do
is make a natural variation
on this theme color.
Now, like we just talked about,
if I want to decrease the
luminosity of this turquoise,
okay, I've got the hue
dialed that looks good.
Let's do the brightness,
that one's really easy.
I know I'm gonna be bringing
this brightness down, right?
So let's try 90%, 80%,
70%, definitely at 70%
this is losing some of that
tropical beach feel right?
This is like the sun is
going down and things
are getting a little bit darker,
this is definitely too dark.
So maybe I bumped it back up to like 80,
maybe kind of low 80s is
about that sweet spot.
And then saturation just as
I brought brightness down,
saturation is gonna move
in the opposite direction,
it's gonna go up a little bit.
So okay, cool, I can
start to saturate this.
And I don't, you know, I don't
need to go to 100, I could,
I suppose that's fine.
But what I'm gonna do for now
is kind of play around
with a value that feels
a little bit closer to just being again,
sort of a natural variation
to this color right here.
Now I can go to this yellow and do kind
of the inverse thing.
Just as I was trying to make the turquoise
a little naturally darker,
I'm gonna try and make
this yellow just a bit brighter.
And so I know the high point
is centered at 60 degrees,
I'll just bump this up a couple degrees,
although I really don't
have to go too much,
or else that yellow is gonna
start feeling greenish,
that's what I don't want.
The saturation, likewise is
going to start going down.
So there we go, 69, what
feels like too much, you know,
maybe 59 definitely by 49
that's starting to feel like too much.
This is a very pale yellow.
So I'll go with a slightly
higher saturation here,
even if I am moving it down somewhat.
And this brightness I'll just bring up
to 100 because of course why not.
There we go.
And that is feeling good to me.
Those two colors seem to
go much better together
than these two right here.
Now of course this is
never the whole story
because you can see right here I've got
this little plus button and it's white
and against this newly brightened yellow,
it is especially difficult to see.
And if I'm ever in a situation
where I need to bring text
in on top, let's say I
have kind of a some text,
I'm defaulting to white on
top of a colored background,
which I should always do for text and UI.
The background is colored, it's
almost guaranteed that white
is gonna be the neatest looking color
for your text on top of
that colored background.
But in this case, it's just
not working like this text
is white and this yellow is
very luminous and overall,
I can't read it whatsoever.
Basically, what I'm saying
is I want more contrast
between the luminosity of my text color
and the luminosity of my background color.
And this issue of text color contrast,
is something we're gonna
dive into in great depth
in the accessibility lesson.
Making software accessible
refers to making sure
that people with different
impairments such as bad eyesight,
or visual impairments, can
use your app very smoothly.
And one important piece
of it is making sure
that your text always contrasts enough
from the background colors.
Knowing about luminosity is a huge help
in solving text contrast issues.
For instance, if I didn't
know anything about luminosity
at all, I might select
these layers and just say,
let's make this text black.
And if I make this text black,
I suppose it could work,
but it kind of ruins some of that light
and airy beach vibe that's
going on throughout the app.
And so I might also want to be able
to explore some other options here.
Well, I basically have two
directions that I can move in.
One is to make this yellow darker such
that it contrasts suitably
against these letters right here.
And the other option is to
make these letters instead
of making them white,
perhaps to make them darker
than the yellow, even if I'm
not just using flat black.
One really useful way to
measure text contrast in Figma,
is to use the plugin
that I plugged earlier
on in this course.
Stark right here, and I
can say check contrast.
And it's gonna tell me that the contrast
between these two selected
layers, the white text layer,
and the yellow background is 1.17 to one.
Now for large texts like this,
where it's of a certain size,
I think 18 pixels is kind of that cut off.
Yeah, there we go.
I need to meet at minimum these guidelines
and for some specific projects,
you may need to meet the triple A level.
But usually you're just
shooting for double A
and I'm supposed to get a
three to one contrast ratio.
Well, 1.17 to one is not very good,
definitely gonna need to
make this stuff darker.
Unfortunately, the free version
of Stark doesn't actually
give you any suggestions
for how to do this, but I
actually have created a tool
and it's linked below that does just this.
You can go paste in whatever
theme color you're using,
you have a couple different
ways of using this.
The first is, it's gonna
show you the closest shade
to the color that you
input that contrasts three
to one against white right here.
And the other option is I can switch
from contrasting against the
color white or some other color
to contrast against itself,
which is gonna give me,
here's the color I input.
And then here is the nearest
variation of that color,
that contrast three to one.
Now this yellow, you can
see it kinda went down
the green direction
where the hue increased,
I don't like that as much.
So if I was using this
tool to try and pick
a better text color,
I'm gonna slide it just a
little bit towards the red side
of things where I get a color
that is much more red here.
And I can go in here and
for my selected color,
paste this new one in.
And if I go to Stark,
which I can always bring
up my last round plugin
by saying option Command P.
I'm gonna see that I now
have a text contrast ratio
of 4.11 to one.
Which actually means that for
large text at double A level,
I've got some kind of wiggle room here I
can play around a little bit.
And honestly, getting text on yellow
can be a tricky problem,
I really need to decide like sometimes
it's gonna look better to have a color
that's almost just more red.
Sometimes an orange is
gonna work good like kind
of a gold feel like that works here.
And I have this trade off where I
can actually do less saturation.
But the less saturation I have,
the more that increases the luminosity,
so I need to counteract it
by going a little bit darker.
So I always have some play here
with exactly what color I want.
But in knowing about luminosity,
I know how can I adjust
the luminosity of the text
so that it contrasts
suitably from the background,
and if needed, meets the
accessibility guidelines
that I need to achieve.
Alright, now let's go look at
a totally different example.
This is just sort of a pricing page
for some sort of service.
It's all kind of general and
the specifics don't matter.
But I want to use it to
demonstrate one other
very important lesson about luminosity,
which is luminosity is absolutely critical
in making elements appear to pop out
of the page or be recessed
down into the page.
So I've got these three cards here.
They're white cards on
a light gray background,
and they definitely
appear to be popping out
of the screen right now.
Now of course you could say,
that's just because they
have shadows, right?
But if I go and I remove those shadows,
they still if you had to judge
are these cards popping out
of the screen or the kind
of recessed into the screen,
it looks more like they're popping out.
And kind of the inverse of this, you know,
if I go and I put an inner shadow
on these three cards right here,
now they're recessed into the screen.
But the light is kinda
gonna make them look
like they're popping out.
And so the inner shadow is sort of working
against the white background here.
It's gonna look more natural,
if I pick a color that
is slightly darker than
that background so let me
do that, hey, there we go.
And now these look much
more convincingly recessed
into the screen, right?
You kind of see, the inner
shadow is now working
with the background color
in the same direction.
Now, that's not what we
want to do, actually,
I'm gonna take away the inner shadow,
add the drop shadows and
move the cards back to white.
The whole point here is that the thing
that makes these cards
appear to pop out even
when there's no shadow,
is the fact that white
is more luminous than this
background color gray.
And so anything that you want
to pop out from the screen,
like let's say some sort
of header or whatever,
I have the option of making
it darker than the background.
But at least I always have
in mind that if I make
it lighter than the background,
it's gonna make it easier to
make it appear popping out
of the screen, you're kind of going
with the grain of the color, so to speak.
And this is not just true
of a grayscale example
like this right here.
I can also do it with color.
So let me take this
card now kind of extend
it just a little bit here,
just so you can really see it kind
of butting up against these other cards,
this is a good thing to do
if I wanna like draw more
attention to the pro option.
And let's say I give all
three of these cards,
a particular background color.
So maybe I'll go pick some, I don't know,
just pick a purple here.
Now one other thing I
should do is now that I
have this purple, I should
make the text color white.
So we'll switch all these
pretty simply and reduce
the opacity of those very nice this works.
But one thing that's gonna
make it work even better
is if I make this front card,
which is popped out even more
than the other two cards,
and you can see it's the
shadow of the front card
that lands on the two cards behind it.
If I make that front
card even more luminous,
or contrastingly, if I make
these back cards less luminous,
now we're just gonna do the
same thing that we always do,
which is decreased luminosity
by increasing saturation
and decreasing brightness.
And there we have it.
Now this front card pops even more.
And so this trick works
when you're dealing
with grayscale cards that
are kinda or elements
that are layered on top of each other.
It works when you're dealing with elements
that have the same hue,
it also works when you're dealing
with elements that have different hues.
So like let's go make this yellow,
just some kind of bright yellow,
find a very bright one here.
That's bright, that's maybe too bright.
Look at this, this now looks awkward,
not just because it's
weirdly asymmetric here
but also or because you
can't read the text,
it just looks awkward
because this yellow demands
to pop out from the screen
because it's so bright,
and yet this purple overshadowing
it just feels kind of weird.
Things are going to feel
much more natural if instead
of having, say colors like this,
and let me just get this one,
I'll just adjust this to like
an orange or something, right?
Like, that seems very, very strange.
And yet, if I kind of
move the background ones
to be a little bit darker
here, do something like a blue
or a purple where there is that kind
of natural darkness to them.
I want to reduce the
saturation a little bit.
And I have the one that's popping
out be naturally brighter,
could just even use this red right here,
that actually looks pretty good.
And just to kind of double
check until we start
to get a real feel for
trusting our eye here,
we can always go to the layer
blend mode and just say,
luminosity blend mode.
And sure enough, what's this, 55.
Okay, it's actually the same
as that one and this one is 50.
So slightly darker.
Now, if all this is true,
by making this look a little bit darker,
not gonna make it too saturated,
should really kind of
help the pop of this red.
And I feel like it does.
So elevation is kind of this
whole other problem where
if you're using luminosity
as you think about elevation,
it's just gonna be a whole
other tool in your toolkit
to help you design exactly
the best looking UI.
Now, one thing to be aware of with this,
especially kind of related
to elevation is shadows.
If I ever have, let's say
a very bright color here,
pick something like
this green or whatever.
I have a bright color here and I put
this in luminosity blend mode,
you're gonna notice something interesting.
I'm gonna press Control P
that's gonna go into pixel mode
and just show me individually what pixels
would look like output on the screen.
You're gonna notice that
there's a very smooth transition
between the shadow and the layer itself.
It's actually kinda
difficult to make out exactly
where the layer begins because
there's not a big difference
between this and that it's
like kind of following
the same pattern of
getting darker every pixel.
Now, that's not to say it's impossible.
But when this happens when you
have a high luminosity layer,
and then you have a nice big shadow on it,
sometimes that shadow will
appear a little bit fuzzy.
And if you look right here, like yeah,
the layer that kind of the bottom
of it looks a little blurred,
I can see it on my screen,
you might need to like, do
this on your own computer
to prove it to yourself here.
But the layer just looks a
little bit blurred at the bottom.
And that's not true of
this blue or this purple.
And that is just because
the luminosity is so high
that it kind of matches the
luminosity of the shadow.
So whenever that happens,
you know, I know,
either I need to make
the layer much lighter,
or I need to make it a little bit darker.
And that's gonna be a big help there.
Now, I don't actually
wanna green layer there
but it's kind of wanted
to talk about one thing
that could happen.
You could have that shadow
fuzzing, if the luminosity
of the layer is not well distinguished
from the luminosity of the shadow.
And that wraps it up for luminosity.
So luminosity, as you can see
is a totally useful concept
in user interface design.
Any issue of text contrast,
luminosity will help you there.
Any issue of elevation,
luminosity is a critical
tool for your toolkit.
And any issue of, what was the
third thing clashing colors,
it's useful there as well.
Now, I also am fully willing
to admit that kind of the way
in which luminosity relates to hue,
saturation and brightness
is pretty confusing.
And right now, it may
feel very awkward and slow
to think and consciously remember each
of these properties and
kinda how to move them to get
the right luminosity for
whatever you're trying to do.
That being said, you will be
applying this again and again.
And at this point, you now
know the building blocks
of the Learn UI Design color system.
Almost all of the rest
of it is just applying
this in a zillion different ways, okay?
So take some heart from that.
There's no homework
per se but do check out
the color cheat sheet which is
linked below if you haven't,
it's a nice printable reference.
And at least until all
this becomes second nature,
it'll help you just have
a really quick guide
into moving hue, saturation and brightness
to achieve different
effects with luminosity.
Alright, from there, we will
see you in the next video.